A Guide to the Virginius Dabney Papers 1932-1958
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Virginius Dabney Papers, 1932-1958
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7690-j
This holding consists of 4 boxes of material.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This holding was acquired as a gift on October 6, 1968.
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Virginius Dabney contain extensive correspondence carried on by Dabney as editor of the Richmond Times-Dispatch, in his personal life, and as a Pulitzer Prize- winning author. Other materials deal with his books such as Below the Potomac, The Dry Messiah, and Liberalism in the South, and much useful material collected as research material for these books is present. There is extensive material on the American Society of Newspaper Editors which Dabney served in various capacities including president. A great deal of useful material on race relations, African Americans, the N.A.A.C.P., etc., is present. Recent political history of Virginia is strongly represented in Dabney's correspondence as editor of Virginia's leading newspaper, and in his personal correspondence with figures such as Senator A. Willis Robinson, Francis Pickens Miller, and Senator Carter Glass.
Contents List
- Correspondence Folder: "American Society of Newspaper Editors" 1951-1952 (Box 1)
- Correspondence Folder: "American Society of Newspaper Editors" 1952-1953 (Box 1)
- Correspondence Folder: [American Society of Newspaper Editors] 1953 (Box 1)
- "Advisory Committee J.L. Loving School of Tailoring" 1949-1952 (Box 1)
- Clippings Folder: "Appeals for Funds Editorials" 1949-1950 (Box 1)
- Liberalism in the South, U.N.C. Press, 1932 1932, TS carbon with ms. corrections, ca. 361 pages (Box 2)
- Liberalism in the South, U.N.C. Press, 1932 1932, TS rough draft, with ms. corrections, ca. 350 pages (Box 2)
- Liberalism in the South, U.N.C. Press, 1932 1932, Research notes, letters, drafts, etc. (Box 3)
- Folder: "Auxiliary II" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1900-1931 Agriculture, Prison Reform, Public Health" (Box 3)
- "1789-1830 Education" (Box 3)
- "1830-1865 Education" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1865-1900 Education" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1900-1931 Education" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1865-1900" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1900-1931" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1930-1932 Letters" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1932 Liberalism" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1789-1830 Literature and Journalism" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1830-1865 Literature and Journalism" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1865-1900 Literature and Journalism" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1900-1931 Literature and Journalism" (Box 3)
- Folder: "Look Up" n.d. (Box 3)
- Folder: "1789-1830 Miscellaneous" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1830-1865 Miscellaneous" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1865-1900 Miscellaneous" (Box 3)
- Folder: "1900-1931 Miscellaneous" (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous unidentified notes n.d. (Box 3)
- Folder: "1789-1830 Politics" (Box 4)
- Folder: "1830-1865 Politics" (Box 4)
- Folder: "1865-1900 Politics" (Box 4)
- Folder: "1900-1931 Politics" (Box 4)
- Folder: "1865-1900 Race Relations" (Box 4)
- Folder: "1900-1931 Race Relations" (Box 4)
- Folder: "1789-1830 Religion" (Box 4)
- Folder: "1830-1865 Religion" (Box 4)
- Folder: "1865-1900 Religion" (Box 4)
- Folder: "1900-1931 Religion" (Box 4)
- Folder: "1789-1830 Slavery" (Box 4)
- Folder: "1830-1865 Slavery" (Box 4)
- Folder: "1900-1931 Woman's Sphere" (Box 4)